Guide to the Sigmund Diamond Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Sigmund Diamond Papers,
[ca. 1950]-1990
Diamond, Sigmund.
52 linear ft. (ca. 62,300 items in 125 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079812
Biographical Note
Sigmund Diamond, (1920-1999),Giddings Professor of Sociology and Emeritus Professor of History, Columbia University, 1955-1986.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, subject files and research notes of Sigmund Diamond. Included among the correspondence are Diamond's letters to and from various distinguished members of Columbia University and other academic insitutions, as well as correspondence with many noted sociologists and historians. Included in the manuscripts is Diamond's "In Quest." The subject files comprise material from Diamond's tenure at Columbia and include some material pertaining to his forced departure from Harvard in the 1950's due to his previous communist affiliation, and his active role in maintaining the efficacy of the Freedom of Information Act. The research files include microfilms and notes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Arranged Manuscripts
Series IV: Subject Files
Series V: Miscellaneous Subject Files
Series VI: Research Files
Series VII: Printed Materials
Subjects
United States.--Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Columbia University.; Columbia University.--Bureau of Applied Social Research.; Harvard University.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Bundy, McGeorge.; Kissinger, Henry, 1923-; Stern, Isaac, 1920-2001.; United States--Social conditions.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; Sociology--Study and teaching.; History--Study and teaching.; Social problems.; Communism--United States.; Addresses.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Budgets.; Financial papers.; Lectures.; Lists.; Memoranda.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Oral histories.; Questionnaires.; Reports.; Reviews.; Speeches.; Surveys.; Tables.; Testimony.; Theses.; Transcripts.; Sociologists.; Authors, American.; College teachers.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-125. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
11/05/1990 M-90-11-05 Diamond Gift
Gift of Sigmund Diamond, 1990.
- Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
  - Isaac Stern (Box I)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Abramovitz - Blackington (Box 1)
  - Blau - Cowan (Box 2)
  - Calligan - Fishmay (Box 3)
  - Fraenkel - Halberstam (Box 4)
  - Hammock - Hurvitz (Box 5)
  - Hurvitz - Lerner (Box 6)
  - Levy - Litwack (Box 7)
  - Lorusso - Miller (Box 8)
  - Mintz - Osherov (Box 9)
  - Oved - Rysman (Box 10)
  - Sacks - Schapiro (Box 11)
  - Shenker - Ward (Box 12)
  - Warshawski - Zuckerman (Box 13)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 14)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 15)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 16)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 17)
  - 1971-1973 (Box 18)
  - 1974-1976 (Box 19)
  - 1977-1979 (Box 20)
  - 1980 (Box 21)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 22)
  - 1982-1984 (Box 23)
  - 1985 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Sociology Department Miscellaneous (Box 26)
- Series III: Arranged Manuscripts
  - "In Quest" (Box 27-28)
  - "In Quest", (Photocopies) (Box 29)
  - "In Quest", (Financial reports, photocopies, miscellaneous) (Box 30)
  - Transcript of oral history (Box 31)
  - Early version of paper delivered at American sociological association (Box 31)
  - "A casual view of America" (Box 31)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - Subseries IV.1: Columbia University
    - GSAS committee Executive committee on curriculum (Box 31a-34)
    - Executive committee Reports & printed material (Box 35-37)
    - Committees, commissions, senate & misc. (Box 38-41)
    - Faculty housing (Box 42)
    - Institute of early American history and culture (Box 42)
    - Fulbright (Box 42)
    - Committees & conferences (Box 43)
    - Sabbaticals (Box 43)
    - Archival correspondence (Box 43)
    - Sub-committee on Ph.D. program in Architecture and urban planning (Box 44)
    - University Senate (Box 45)
    - University housing & rent protests (Box 46)
    - Bicentennial celebration (Box 47)
    - --Hudson institute project (Box 47)
    - --Evaluation--Rutgers (Box 47)
    - School of Public Health (Box 48)
    - Commission on academic priorities in arts & sciences (Box 49)
    - --Disciplinary committee (Box 49)
    - --Student disorders (Box 49)
  - Series IV.2: Sociology Department
    - Chairperson of sociology dept. (Box 50)
    - Director of graduate studies (Box 51-53)
    - Oral exams (Box 54 & 55)
    - Student papers (Box 56-61)
    - Ph.D dissertations (Box 62-69)
    - Sociology department --Legitimation --Historical sociology for graduates (Box 70)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 71)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Subject Files
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 72)
  - ACLS (Box 73)
  - Behavioral & Social Sciences Survey Committee (Box 74)
  - Book reviews (Box 75)
  - Conferences & trips (Box 76)
  - Etzioni, Amitai (Box 77-79)
  - Grants (Box 80)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 81)
  - National Research Council Behavior modification therapy (Box 82)
  - Political Science Quarterly (Box 83)
  - --Jewish Social Studies (Box 83)
  - Publishers - contracts, correspondence (Box 84)
  - Serge Lang (Box 85-86)
  - Miscellaneous academic: National science fund; Short term lectureships; Dirctor of scholars, 1979-80; Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 87)
  - Institute for Advanced Studies NYU appointment & lectures, Vassar (Box 88)
- Series VI: Research Files
  - Anti-semitism (Box 89-90)
  - Bilingualism project (Box 91-92)
  - Freedom of information (Box 93-94)
  - Jewish materials - organizations & projects (Box 95-97)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 98-99)
  - Notes for bibliography on background of civilization & notes on colonization (Box 100)
  - Miscellaneous notes on notecards (Box 100-104)
  - Photocopies from archives nationales & bibliotheque nationale (Box 105-108)
  - Microfilm from archives de ministere (Box 109-112)
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  - Articles, speeches & reprints (Box 113-123)
  - Offprints inscribed (Box 124)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 125)